Guide to the Waterbury Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Waterbury family papers
1700-1966
1750-1897
MS 537
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
(4 boxes)
Correspondence, financial records, and memorabilia of this Stamford, Connecticut family. The principal figure is David Waterbury (1722-1801), who served as a colonel in the French and Indian War and again in the American Revolution. Included in the papers are military records relating to these events and a letter to him from Roger Sherman (1776 Apr 30) about a Continental Commission. Also two travel journals kept by his son, William Waterbury IV, one for a trip throught New York, Pennsylvania, Virginia, Kentucky, Maryland and Delaware in 1799-1800 and another for a trip through New York State in 1812-1813.
Waterbury family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Sara Mead Webb and Walter Edward Leaman, Jr., in 1964, and of Mrs. John L. Waterbury in 1981.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Due to the physical nature of the mug and ring in box 4, staff supervision is required.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of correspondence, financial records, and memorabilia of the Waterbury family of Stamford, Connecticut, and of military papers belonging to David Waterbury (1722-1801). Included among these is an orderly book (1758-59) and orders for Brigadier General Benedict Arnold at Ticonderoga (1776 Aug 7). The correspondence contains both family and general letters, the most interesting being a letter from Roger Sherman to David Waterbury concerning a Continental Commission (1776 Apr 30). The financial and legal papers of the family include an indenture from 1700, account books, and deeds, while the highlight of the memorabilia is a series of diaries kept by William Waterbury IV (the son of David Waterbury) during travels through New York, Pennsylvania, Virginia, Maryland, and Delaware in 1799-1800 and New York in 1812-13.
Biographical / Historical
David Waterbury (1722-1801): military officer; served in six campaigns in the French and Indian Wars; appointed Brigadier General, 1776; served 23 successive terms as Stamford representative in the Connecticut legislature.
Armed Forces; Families; Connecticut; New York (State) -- Description and travel; Stamford (Conn.); United States -- Description and travel; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; United States -- History -- French and Indian War, 1754-1763; United States -- Revolution, 1755-1783; Diaries; Soldiers; Dyer, Eliphalet, 1721-1807; Lyman, Daniel, 1718-1788; Sherman, Roger, 1721-1793; Waterbury, David, 1722-1801; Waterbury, Mary Maltbie, 1733-1810; Waterbury, Silvanus; Waterbury, William, 1765-1842; Waterbury family
- Inventory, 1700-1966
  - Correspondence
    - ALS to David Waterbury from David Lyman, 1774 November 26 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - ALS to David Waterbury from [Hezekiah Ripley?], 1775 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - ALS to Mary Waterbury and children from David Waterbury, 1775 August 6 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - ALS to Mary Waterbury and children from David Waterbury, 1775 September 8 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - ALS to Mary Waterbury and children from David Waterbury, 1775 September 20 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Photostat of ALS to Mary Waterbury from David Waterbury, 1775 November 3 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - ALS to David Waterbury from Mary Waterbury, 1776 February 23 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - ALS to David Waterbury from Mary Waterbury, 1776 March 7 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - ALS to David Waterbury from Eliphalet Dyer, 1776 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - ALS to David Waterbury from Roger Sherman, 1776 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - ALS to David Waterbury from William Tennant, 1776 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - AL to Silvanus Waterbury from an unidentified correspondent, 1777 January 4 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - ALS to William Waterbury from George B. Smythe, 1841 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Electrostatic copy of TLS to Mrs. John Waterbury from David C. Mearns, 1956 June 19 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Military Papers
    - Photostatic copies of officer's commission for David Waterbury, 1755 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Captain David Waterbury's orderly book, 1758-1759 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Orders and instructions for Brigadier General Benedict Arnold at Ticonderoga, 1776 August 7 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - A Complete Roster of Colonel David Waterbury Jr.'s Regiment of Connecticut Volunteers, by A. H. Clark, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Financial and Legal Papers
    - Indenture by George Hurt, 1700 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Account book concerning the estate of Timothy Jessup, 1809 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Account book of William Waterbury IV [son of David Waterbury], 1812-1834 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Deed of land sale between Naomi Webb and Theodore Waterbury [son of William Waterbury IV], 1845 June 2 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Deed from Naomi Webb to Theodore Waterbury, 1851 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Deed from George Jessup to Theodore Waterbury, 1857 November 16 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Sketch of a parcel of land with bordering owners, Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Memorabilia
    - Two travel diaries kept by William Waterbury IV on his trips though New York, Pennsylvania, Virginia, Maryland, and Delaware, 1799-1800 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Two travel diaries kept by William Waterbury IV on his trips to New York, 1812-1813 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Universal Spelling Book owned by William Waterbury IV, Circa 1756 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Handwritten book by Molly Waterbury [daughter of David Waterbury] containing poems, hymns, and a letter to an aunt, Undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Poem, "The Beggar and the Divine," by Jesse Hoyt, Undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Poem, "Why do we mourn departed friends," [by Molly Waterbury?], Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Recipe for General Waterbury's punch, Undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1923, 1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Family Bible, 1761 (Box 3)
    - Mug and ring, Undated (Box 4)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Due to the physical nature of the mug and ring in box 4, staff supervision is required.